Guide to the C. C. Van Arsdol Papers 1887-1961
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
C. C. Van Arsdol Papers
1887-1961
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA, 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 103
Van Arsdol, Ted
.75 feet of linear shelf space 2 boxes
Typescript transcripts, prepared by C. C. Van Arsdol's grandson, Ted Van Arsdol, of correspondence and reports dating from 1887-1961 about railroad construction in Washington and Idaho, construction of Lewiston Grade Highway, and other consulting services.
C. C. Van Arsdol (1851-1941) began his career in civil engineering when he attended a civil engineering course at Iowa State University in 1876. Shortly after, Van Arsdol became chief draughtsman for the Union Pacific Railway in 1880. He was later given the duties associated with the reconnaissance and preliminary location in the district around Lewiston, Idaho, the Snake River, and the Salmon River. In 1903, Van Arsdol worked for the Grand Trunk Pacific Railway, where he controlled all the work from Saskatoon west to the Pacific Ocean until World War I began in 1914. Following the war, he returned to Lewiston, Idaho and worked as a consulting engineer.
This collection consists of typescript transcripts, prepared by C. C. Van Arsdol's grandson, Ted Van Arsdol, of correspondence and reports dating from 1887-1961 about railroad construction in Washington and Idaho, construction of Lewiston Grade Highway, and other consulting services. Also includes photographs (prints and negatives) of the railroad survey of Hells Canyon (Snake River), 1928.
This collection is arranged in a single series.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection was donated to Washington State University Libraries between 1960 and 1962 by Ted Van Arsdol, grandson of C. C. Van Arsdol.
Van Arsdol, C. C. (Cassius Cash), 1851-1941
Lewiston Grade (Idaho); Snake River (Wyo.-Wash.) -- Description and travel
Roads -- Idaho -- Lewiston -- Design and construction -- History -- Sources; Railroads -- Northwest, Pacific -- Design and construction; Roads -- Idaho -- Nez Perce County; Engineers -- Washington (State) -- Clarkston -- Correspondence
Railroads; Washington (State); Idaho; Photographs
- Career, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence and Prospectus: "Rocky Fork and Cooke City Railway Company", 1887 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and G. W. Hunt and "The Hunt Road", 1890s (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1896-1898 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- G. W. Hunt and "The Hunt Road", 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous reports, 1903-1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Honoring C. C. Van Arsdol's life, 1937-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Report from the file of C. C. Van Arsdol, consulting engineer, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Hells Canyon photographs, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 15-20)